<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://blog.startupforstartups.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://blog.startupforstartups.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2026-03-01T12:46:54+00:00</updated><id>https://blog.startupforstartups.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Startup For Startups</title><subtitle>Resume writing tips and advice</subtitle><author><name>Team SFS</name></author><entry><title type="html">What questions a software engineer address in their resume?</title><link href="https://blog.startupforstartups.com/what-questions-a-software-engineering-address-in-their-resume" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What questions a software engineer address in their resume?" /><published>2024-10-12T14:01:15+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-12T14:01:15+00:00</updated><id>https://blog.startupforstartups.com/what-questions-a-software-engineering-address-in-their-resume</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.startupforstartups.com/what-questions-a-software-engineering-address-in-their-resume"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>Most software engineers focus on technologies they have used and completely miss to tell the story of their work experience.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Following is a list of questions your resume <em>must</em> answer:</p>

<h2 id="questions-about-projects">Questions about projects</h2>

<ol>
  <li>What was the scale of your software? How many users did it serve?</li>
  <li>How critical was your project for the business?</li>
  <li>What was the impact of your project on the business? How was it measured?</li>
  <li>Was the project challenging? What was the most challenging part?</li>
  <li>Was it a new project or enhancement of an existing one?</li>
  <li>Did you provide technical support for the project?</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="questions-about-teams">Questions about teams</h2>

<ol>
  <li>Did you work in a multidisciplinary team? Did you work with non-software engineers?</li>
  <li>How did you measure the success of your project? And your contribution to it?</li>
  <li>Were you involved in the hiring process?</li>
  <li>Did you mentor junior engineers?</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="questions-about-technologies">Questions about technologies</h2>

<ol>
  <li>Did you learn any new technology for the project?</li>
  <li>How was the new technology selected?</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="questions-about-business">Questions about business</h2>

<ol>
  <li>Did you work with the business team? How did you communicate with them?</li>
  <li>Did you have any interaction with the end-users?</li>
  <li>How is the business impact of your project measured?</li>
</ol>]]></content><author><name>Team SFS</name></author><category term="Software Resume" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What questions a software engineer address in their resume?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Introducing Resume Review Service.</title><link href="https://blog.startupforstartups.com/introducing-resume-review-service" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introducing Resume Review Service." /><published>2024-09-23T13:29:33+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-23T13:29:33+00:00</updated><id>https://blog.startupforstartups.com/introducing-resume-review-service</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.startupforstartups.com/introducing-resume-review-service"><![CDATA[<p>We are excited to announce the launch of our new <a href="https://reviewer.startupforstartups.com/">Resume Review Service</a>.</p>

<p>Instead of purely relying on AI to review your resume, we have AI and a team of <strong>experts</strong> to review your resume and give you personalized feedback.</p>

<p>Our team has years of experience in recruiting and hiring, and we know what employers are looking for in a resume. We will review your resume for formatting, content, and overall effectiveness, and provide you with actionable feedback on how to make it better.</p>

<p>Our service uses artificial intelligence to analyze your resume and provide you with personalized feedback.</p>

<p>We do however understand that resume is one of the most important tools in your job search, and our <strong>experts</strong> will provide you with in depth feedback, taking into consideration industry requirements to stand out from your competition.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Most candidates fail to get shortlisted because of their resume. We are here to help you get shortlisted for your dream job.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>PS - Our service is completely <strong>free</strong>!</p>]]></content><author><name>Team SFS</name></author><category term="General" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Introducing Resume Review Service.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What information should you include in an effective cover letter?</title><link href="https://blog.startupforstartups.com/what-information-should-you-include-in-an-effective-cover-letter" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What information should you include in an effective cover letter?" /><published>2024-09-21T08:22:45+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-21T08:22:45+00:00</updated><id>https://blog.startupforstartups.com/what-information-should-you-include-in-an-effective-cover-letter</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.startupforstartups.com/what-information-should-you-include-in-an-effective-cover-letter"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>Majority of candidates re-use the same cover letter for every job application.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Here is how you can easily stand out from the crowd by including the right information in your cover letter.</p>

<h2 id="demonstrate-you-have-skills-and-experience-for-the-job">Demonstrate you have skills and experience for the job</h2>

<p>Take 3 most important skills and experiences from the job description and write 2-3 lines for each one. Include examples of how you have used these skills in the past. Make sure to use the same <em>language</em> as the job description.
Ensure that you are not just repeating your resume.</p>

<h2 id="demonstrate-you-will-fit-in-with-the-team">Demonstrate you will fit in with the team</h2>

<p>A good job description will include information about how the team works together. You should include a sentence about how you have worked in a similar team in the past. This shows the hiring manager that you will fit in with the team.
If you have not worked in a similar team before, you can include a sentence about how you are looking forward to working in a similar team and why.</p>

<h2 id="show-you-have-researched-the-company">Show you have researched the company</h2>

<p>Most companies will have a vision and mission statement. Many will also have a set of values. You should include pick a value that is most important to you and demonstrate how in your past you have lived up to that value. This shows the hiring manager that you have done your research and are genuinely interested in the company.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You should include these 5 points; 3 for skills, 1 for team-fit, 1 for company-fit; to have an effective cover letter that will make sure your resume stands out.</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name>Team SFS</name></author><category term="Cover Letter" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[what information should you include in an effective cover letter?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Should you use AI to write your resume?</title><link href="https://blog.startupforstartups.com/should-you-use-ai-to-write-your-resume" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Should you use AI to write your resume?" /><published>2024-09-19T10:07:19+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-19T10:07:19+00:00</updated><id>https://blog.startupforstartups.com/should-you-use-ai-to-write-your-resume</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.startupforstartups.com/should-you-use-ai-to-write-your-resume"><![CDATA[<p>AI is changing the way we work, and it is also changing the way we write resumes. Should you use AI to write your resume? Let’s find out.</p>

<p>AI tools such as ChatGPT, Claude, and other are extremely useful to write your resume. They can help you write a resume that is tailored to the job you are applying for. They can also help you write a resume that is free from errors and typos.</p>

<p>However, you should be judicious in using AI to write your resume.</p>

<p>Your experience, work history and achievements are unique to you. AI tools can help you write a resume, but they cannot replace your unique voice and perspective.</p>

<p>Here are some tips to use AI to write your resume:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Write down as much as you can about your work summary, experience, and achievements in your own voice.</li>
  <li>Use AI tools to refine your resume, correct errors, and make it more readable.</li>
  <li>Make sure generated output AI does not sound robotic. It should sound like you.</li>
  <li>When providing context to AI, ensure you highlight why a certain achievement is important and how it impacted the business.</li>
</ol>

<blockquote>
  <p>AI tools can help you write a resume, but they cannot replace your unique voice and perspective.</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name>Team SFS</name></author><category term="Resume Writing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Should you use AI to write your resume?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What is a cover letter?</title><link href="https://blog.startupforstartups.com/what-is-a-cover-letter" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is a cover letter?" /><published>2024-09-19T08:20:43+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-19T08:20:43+00:00</updated><id>https://blog.startupforstartups.com/what-is-a-cover-letter</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.startupforstartups.com/what-is-a-cover-letter"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>A cover letter is a document that you send with your resume to provide demonstrate your skills and experience for the job you are applying for.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>A resume contains your work history and skills. It is usually same for all the jobs you apply for.</p>

<p>Whereas a cover letter is written specifically for the job you are applying for.</p>

<p>An effective cover letter is used to:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Demonstrate that you have read through the job des##cription and understood requirements.</li>
  <li>Show that you have demonstrated skills and experience for this specific job.</li>
  <li>Show that you have researched the company and are genuinely interested in working there.</li>
  <li>Show that you will fit in with the team.</li>
</ol>

<blockquote>
  <p>Do not copy-paste same cover letter for every job application. Make sure to customize it for each job you apply for.</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name>Team SFS</name></author><category term="Cover Letter" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What is a cover letter?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Common resume format mistakes to avoid.</title><link href="https://blog.startupforstartups.com/common-resume-format-mistakes-to-avoid" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Common resume format mistakes to avoid." /><published>2024-09-19T06:25:24+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-19T06:25:24+00:00</updated><id>https://blog.startupforstartups.com/common-resume-format-mistakes-to-avoid</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.startupforstartups.com/common-resume-format-mistakes-to-avoid"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>Most resumes have a lot of visual distraction making it harder to read and understand.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Common mistakes to avoid when formatting your resume:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Using a lot of colors</strong>: At most use three colors, white for background, very dark gray for text, and a color to highlight few very key points.</li>
  <li><strong>Using a lot of fonts</strong>: Use a single font for the entire resume, and use different font weights to differentiate between headings and body text.</li>
  <li><strong>Unreadable font</strong>: Use a font that is readable, make sure line height is good, and font size is not too small.</li>
  <li><strong>Avoid multiple columns</strong>: Use a single column layout, it is easier to read and understand.</li>
  <li><strong>Avoid using tables</strong>: Tables force you to have headings, so part of the information is elsewhere, making it harder to read. For example is it year of graduation or year of enrolment?</li>
  <li><strong>Separate sections</strong>: Make sure each section is clearly separated from the other sections, use higher margins or dividers.</li>
</ol>]]></content><author><name>Team SFS</name></author><category term="Resume Format" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Common resume format mistakes to avoid.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What is an applicant tracking system?</title><link href="https://blog.startupforstartups.com/what-is-an-applicant-tracking-system" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is an applicant tracking system?" /><published>2024-09-11T09:13:01+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-11T09:13:01+00:00</updated><id>https://blog.startupforstartups.com/what-is-an-applicant-tracking-system</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.startupforstartups.com/what-is-an-applicant-tracking-system"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>Applicant tracking system, or ATS, is a process software used by recruitments to improve efficiency of recruitment process.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="what-is-an-applicant-tracking-system">What is an applicant tracking system?</h2>

<p>It is a <strong>process management</strong> software used by recruitment teams to improve their efficiency.</p>

<p>It commonly provides features such as:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Job posting</strong>: Post job openings to various job boards and social media platforms.</li>
  <li><strong>Resume parsing</strong>: Automatically parse resumes and extract relevant information.</li>
  <li><strong>Candidate tracking</strong>: Track candidates through the recruitment process.</li>
  <li><strong>Interview scheduling</strong>: Schedule interviews with candidates.</li>
  <li><strong>Reporting</strong>: Generate reports on recruitment process.</li>
  <li><strong>Feedback</strong>: Collect feedback from interviewers and candidates.</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="myths-about-applicant-tracking-systems">Myths about applicant tracking systems</h2>

<p>Biggest myth candidates have is, ATS uses some keyword matching and resumes that do not contain these keywords are automatically rejected.</p>

<p>This is not true. ATS is a tool to help recruiters manage their recruitment process, not to reject candidates.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>If you have read through job description and are sure you qualify for it at even 50% level, apply for it. ATS will not reject you just because you did not use the right keywords.</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name>Team SFS</name></author><category term="- ResumeWriting " /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What is an applicant tracking system?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Don’t include obsolete technologies in your resume.</title><link href="https://blog.startupforstartups.com/dont-include-obsolete-technologies-in-your-resume" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Don’t include obsolete technologies in your resume." /><published>2024-09-10T09:00:26+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-10T09:00:26+00:00</updated><id>https://blog.startupforstartups.com/dont-include-obsolete-technologies-in-your-resume</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.startupforstartups.com/dont-include-obsolete-technologies-in-your-resume"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>Many candidates include obsolete technologies in their resume. This is a mistake. You should only include technologies that are relevant today.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Subversion (SVN) was once a cutting edge technology, but it is not anymore, and rarely anyone cares if you know it.</p>

<p>The same goes for many other technologies. If you include them in your resume, you are providing information that is no longer relevant.</p>

<p>Software industry is fast-paced. Technologies come and go. You should keep your resume up-to-date with the latest technologies.</p>]]></content><author><name>Team SFS</name></author><category term="ResumeWriting" /><category term="Software" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Don't include obsolete technologies in your resume.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What information you should not include in your resume?</title><link href="https://blog.startupforstartups.com/what-information-you-should-not-include-in-your-resume" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What information you should not include in your resume?" /><published>2024-09-09T18:36:46+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-09T18:36:46+00:00</updated><id>https://blog.startupforstartups.com/what-information-you-should-not-include-in-your-resume</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.startupforstartups.com/what-information-you-should-not-include-in-your-resume"><![CDATA[<p>Most resumes contain information that is not necessary and can be left out. Removing this information can help you create a more concise and effective resume.</p>

<p>Here are some things you should not include in your resume:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Languages you speak. Unless the job requires you to speak a specific language, you should not include this information on your resume.</li>
  <li>Personal information such as your age or marital status. This information is not relevant to the job and can be left out.</li>
  <li>References. You do not need to include references on your resume. Instead, you can provide them when requested.</li>
  <li>Salary information. You should not include your salary history or expectations on your resume.</li>
  <li>Hobbies and interests. Only include hobbies that you excel in. If you can play the guitar like a pro, then include it. Otherwise, leave it out.</li>
  <li>Objective statement. Instead of an objective statement, include a summary of your qualifications and experience.</li>
  <li>High school information. Unless you are a recent graduate, you do not need to include high school information on your resume.</li>
  <li>Irrelevant work experience. Only include work experience that is relevant to the job you are applying for.</li>
  <li>Social media profiles. Only include social media profiles that are relevant to the job. For example, if you are applying for a marketing position, you can include your LinkedIn profile.</li>
</ol>]]></content><author><name>Team SFS</name></author><category term="Resume Writing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What information you should not include in your resume?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What information should you include in your resume?</title><link href="https://blog.startupforstartups.com/what-information-should-you-include-in-your-resume" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What information should you include in your resume?" /><published>2024-09-06T15:53:24+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-06T15:53:24+00:00</updated><id>https://blog.startupforstartups.com/what-information-should-you-include-in-your-resume</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.startupforstartups.com/what-information-should-you-include-in-your-resume"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>Resume is a brief summary of your professional skills, achievements, and experience.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="what-information-should-you-include-in-your-resume">What information should you include in your resume?</h2>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Contact Information</strong>: Include your name, phone number, email address, and location.</li>
  <li><strong>Summary</strong>: Write a brief summary of your professional skills, achievements, and experience.</li>
  <li><strong>Experience</strong>: List your work experience in reverse chronological order.</li>
  <li><strong>Education</strong>: Include your educational background, including degrees, certifications, and relevant coursework.</li>
  <li><strong>Key Skills</strong>: List your <em>key</em> skills, maximum five.</li>
  <li><strong>Volunteer Experience</strong>: Include any volunteer work you have done.</li>
  <li><strong>Hobbies and Interests</strong>: Include any hobbies or interest, only if you are excellent at it. If you play piano at semi-professional level, include it. If your hobby is watching movies, don’t include it.</li>
  <li><strong>Portfolio</strong>: Include a link to your portfolio, if you have one. If you have professional social media, include those links as well, for example - GitHub/dribble/behance.</li>
  <li><strong>Spoken Languages</strong>: Include the languages you speak, read, and write, only if knowledge of these languages will give you an advantage in the job for example sales or customer support roles.</li>
</ol>]]></content><author><name>Team SFS</name></author><category term="- ResumeWriting " /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What information should you include in your resume?]]></summary></entry></feed>